שבוע טוב Shavua Tov everybody. We're on שבועות Shavuos 3 today
and we pick up right after the very long משנה Mishnah which
is really the entire it's the משנה Mishnah for the entire פרק
Perek and the משנה Mishnah very quickly because of the structure of
two which is four which applies by שבועות Shevuos there are two
in the past there are two in the future. It goes into
a whole series of two which is four about different types of
ways in which a person is טמא tamei and enters into
the temple בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or
eats קרבנות korbanos and would bring the sacrifice of עולה ויורד. Oleh
Veyored. I think I erased it anyway the sacrifice of of going
up and down. And then we got into some other twos and
fours but with this high focus
on this issue about impurity of the מקדש Mikdash of the temple
right and about the ways in which and the different things which
would atone for it. So you have the personal קרבן korban of
עולה ויורד Oleh Veyored of changing value when it was known at
the beginning and then forgotten and known at the end and then
all these different sacrifices of יום כיפור Yom Kippur that had to
deal with different and then of the ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh and
the רגלים Regalim that had to deal with different ways in which
atoning for this sin. And of course the point we made or
continue to make is that in the תורה Torah of course יום
כיפור Yom Kippur is very focused on cleansing the מקדש Mikdash but
that's more metaphysical cleansing of the מקדש Mikdash because the way all
sin is seen to impurify the מקדש Mikdash whereas in the משנה
Mishnah it's like it's strange all of the heightened focus you know
sacrifices or whatever of יום כיפור Yom Kippur the thing we make
such a big deal about you know it sort of in the
משנה Mishnah here it loses the metaphysical focus of cleansing the מקדש
Mikdash and focuses more on atoning for individual sins when they accidentally
entered into the מקדש Mikdash when they were impure. So that's obviously
anyway that's the emphasis of the משנה Mishnah and then the משנה
Mishnah says oh but by the way for all other sins whether
whether willful מזיד meizid or שוגג shogeg whether you know you don't
know even if they're ones deserving of the death penalty or even
if they're light ones that basically you know the goat that you
send off the edge of the cliff on יום כיפור Yom Kippur
atones for. So that was like okay we like are now way
way far from the opening theme about שבועות. Shavuos. But this raises
the theme I think to me this might be an indication of
why we spend the first two chapters of שבועות Shavuos dealing with
this these issues of the impurity of the מקדש. Mikdash. I mean
we have two chapters which is a complete digression and the גמרא
Gemara is going to get to that question but at least one
answer for me is the last line is the end of this
משנה Mishnah is you know we just finished all of סנהדרין Sanhedrin
and מכות Makkos which is about all the death penalties for all
the penalties for transgression right all the death penalties and the lashes
and the going into the exile right all of the punishments of
the court. So the question is how do we think about that
like how do we think about all that weightiness of transgression and
so on and all the sin etc. So if you remember the
end of מכות Makkos had an answer to that right the end
of מכות Makkos was that because oh no no no no this
is all just לזכות את ישראל lezakos es Yisrael this is all
just to make things easier for you. All you have to do
is sit at home and do absolutely nothing and you get tons
of reward for not transgressing okay so that's like reframing all of
these heavy transgressions as just don't do them and you'll get an
enormous reward and reframing it in a positive way. Well our משנה
Mishnah has another answer for it right our משנה Mishnah says no
matter how bad the sin even if it's intentional even if it's
one of those sins that you're deserving of the death penalty for
which we learned about in the you know in סנהדרין Sanhedrin you
know just this one ritual on יום כיפור Yom Kippur they send
the goat over the cliff and that's it it's atoned for you
right. So I think that partly a little bit of what this
is doing is a little bit of of going back to you
know the weight of what we learned throughout סנהדרין Sanhedrin and מכות.
Makkos. The other thing that I would suggest in terms of why
all of this emphasis that explains maybe the end of the משנה
Mishnah but nevertheless the majority of the פרק Perek is devoted to
the issues of you know the impurity of the מקדש Mikdash right
so what does that have to do with anything. So here's just
a thought that I had which is since we're going to be
using we can sort of explore this as we continue to learn
but since the theme of this פרק Perek is the using of
the שבועה Shavuah of a שבועה Shevuah I gotta be careful I'm
going to say שבועות Shavuot again you were I know did I
say it earlier also already oh my god I gotta really correct
that okay fine anyway oh my god anyway שבועה Shavuah since the
whole מסכת Masechet is the use of the שבועה Shavuah of the
oath right as a way of determining truth taking an oath in
court
and so on so the question is like how is that really
going to do the job how weightily is you know a שבועה
Shavuah perceived and so on. So on the one hand right the
opening here that it's sort of in somewhat just by juxtaposition and
it's the same type of
קרבן korban when you take a false oath as the impurity of
the מקדש Mikdash and impurifying of the מקדש Mikdash is the thing
that you know is the center. center of all of these sacrifices
on יום כיפור Yom Kippur and ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh and the
רגלים regalim and so on, some degree suggests an issue also, I
mean just by association of the weight of also a oath and
a false oath. And maybe I would push it a little further
and say, you know, the whole question is in the absence of
the מקדש, mikdash, right, where is God sort of present in this
world? In the absence of a temple. When you invoke an oath,
and in a standard as is in the name of God, either
explicitly or implicitly in the name of God, right, you're sort of
like bringing God into the world to testify to the veracity of
what you are saying. And then when you are lying, you are
sort of like, you know, defiling that. So there's an aspect I
would argue of sort of of מטמא המקדש, metamei hamikdash, right, impurifying
the temple when you take a false oath. Right, without a temple,
like the place of God where God's name is invoke, or evoke,
evoke, invoke in this world, right, that's like the place of God
and then you violate that by your false oath. So I think
at least in my mind I'm struggling with why devote two chapters
of a מסכת masechet that is all about oaths to this issue
about impurifying the temple, right? And I think to some degree it
might be around this issue about a certain type of analogy that
is being drawn. Okay, so with that we'll start the גמרא, gemara,
yes.
How would the atonement of יום כיפור Yom Kippur help with somebody
who's a sin against another person who would get the סנהדרין's Sanhedrin
judgment? I mean how would that... Right, so yeah, so it only
sort
of straightens you up with God. Any sort of, by the way,
a person that's also interesting thing, a person could repent and... They'd
still be killed. Right, exactly. You know, we down here have to
do human justice, so a person could do the best, the greatest
תשובה teshuvah in the world and be atoned for on יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, and that's as far as God is concerned. The court
down here will still, you know, you still have to have justice
in this world, whatever. So, and, you know, now it is interesting
that in our secular system, right, a person basically, I mean it's
not enough that they repent, you know, there's a process of parole
and this and that. So and, you know, it's not like, oh
you know, if a person really overnight completely repented, you know, he's
not up for parole for 20 years. It doesn't matter that he
completely repented even if we could see straight into his soul. Besides
the challenge that you can't see straight into a person's soul. Okay?
So the system of justice, you know, can't allow and even in
secular justice only allows in extremely limited ways for taking into account,
you know, regret and, and so on, transformation etc. But also when
it's a sin between people, that's if, you know, that's even if
a person broke שבת, Shabbos, God might totally forgive him but the
בית דין Beis Din might still execute him. But a sin between
people, it's true, our משנה Mishnah did not mention, it's mentioned in
יומא Yoma that the qualification or, you know, the limit on the
idea of what יום כיפור Yom Kippur atones for is sins between
people. You know, you have to make right with God but you
can't make it right with God until you've
made it right with the person that you've injured, right? So yes,
that's an important, you know, qualification. Yes, Charlie.
So this section feels like it ought to be in סדר קדשים,
Seder Kodashim, but also the מסכת הוריות Masechet Horayos also feels like
it should be... Right, but הוריות Horayos is different. הוריות Horayos you're
dealing with sacrifices because that's the sacrifice you bring for the issue
which is the topic of the מסכת. masechet. This is completely off.
All of these sacrifices have nothing to do with issues of שבועות.
Shavuos. They have to do with issues of entering the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash.
So would you argue that the court executing someone for violation of
שבת Shabbat is God's justice, you know, but if God's forgiven you...
Alright, so whatever, anyway, we're getting way off the topic. But the
bottom line, yes, but the bottom line is that how do we
know? Can we see into somebody's soul? You know. Alright, but anyway,
that's an interesting question and it's discussed, I think there's a famous
תשובה teshuvah of the נודע ביהודה Noda BiYehuda about that, but that's
not our issue now. Let's take a look at the גמרא. gemara.
מכדי, Michti, okay, so that's my sort of thoughts about why we've
just we have two chapters devoted to this issue about טומאת מקדש,
tumat mikdash, but let's see what the גמרא gemara has to say
about this. מכדי, Michti, תנא מהיכא סליק? tanna me-heicha salik? Our תנא
tanna just left off, meaning this tractate follows מכות. Makkos. מאי שנא
דתני שבועות? Mai shena de-tani Shavuos? So why does שבועות Shavuot come
after מכות? Makkos? So they're not, you know, they're not asking our
question about why this discussion of טומאת מקדש. tumat mikdash. Why does
this whole tractate come after מכות? Makkos? The answer of course all
the scholars say is is that it's based on size and order
of chapters and number of chapters. And even though of course שבועות
Shavuos has many more chapters than מכות, Makkos, but if you think
of סנהדרין Sanhedrin and מכות Makkos as one big tractate, which is
what it seems to be, then שבועות Shavuos is
the next tractate based on size. But let's see what the גמרא
gemara says. משום דתני, Mishum de-tani, because right at the end of
מכות, Makkos, one of the משניות Mishnayot was: חייב על הראש שתים
אחת מכאן ואחת מכאן ועל הזקן חמש שתים מכאן ושתים מכאן ואחת
מלמטה. Chayav al harosh shtayim, achat mikan ve-achat mikan, ve-al hazakan chamesh,
shtayim mikan ve-shtayim mikan ve-achat mi-lemata. So there are two corners of
the of your sideburns which you transgress if you shave them off,
you know, and there's five corners of your beard. beard the ending
two of the sideburns and like two here and one here, and
you get lashes, you can get up to five lashes if you
shave them all off at once, okay. So because that was two
and two and then two and one, so there is a whole
two here and five here, it is sort of like two and
four, okay. So חד דמחייב אטרתי, chad demichayeiv atartei, so that is
one thing you could get two lashes if you shave off one
sideburn with one warning and you do it תוך כדי דיבור, toch
kedei dibbur, you do both sideburns at the same time, you will
get two sets of lashes or whatever it is, okay. So actually
wait, I think I missaid it, the corners here are here, here
are the corners for whatever, does not matter, here are the corners
for the sideburn, one here and one here, okay, so and whatever,
does not matter, okay fine, and then the beard is one, two,
two, four, five, okay, five corners in the beard. Yeah, but anyway,
but if you do them both at the same time or you
do the beard all תוך כדי דיבור toch kedei dibbur with the
warning, you get five lashes. Okay. So okay, חד דמחייב אטרתי, chad
demichayeiv atartei, so you get two punishments for the price of one,
okay, so תנא שבועות שתים שהן ארבע, tana shevuos shtayim shehein arba,
so that led to the same discussion of two which is four
which is שבועות, shevuos, that is pretty weak. מאי שנא הכא דתני
להו לכולהו? mai shna hacha detani lehu lekulhu? Now we have a
couple of things of two which is four. Two which is four
of the oaths, two which is four of טומאה, tumah, two which
is four of the צרעת, tzaraas, and two which is four of
שבת. Shabbos. Now if you go to each one of those tractates,
except for the טומאת tumah for entering into the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash which does not have a tractate, but if you go to
the beginning of שבת, Shabbos, you have the two which is four
as the opening משנה Mishnah of שבת. Shabbos. And if you go
to the נגעים, Negaim, the tractate dealing with צרעת, tzaraas, with leprosy,
you have the two which is four line there. But in each
of those you only have the one part of that list that
is relevant to that tractate. Here we collected all of them. Okay.
So now that actually happens a lot. In earlier collections of משניות,
Mishnayos, you have a collection of things that have a similar type
of a structure, even though thematically they are not the same. Probably
the best example is in מגילה, Megillah, where it says אין בין,
ein bein, there is no difference between X and Y except this,
and then you go on to twenty different topics. Okay. So and
then maybe what happens is those things begin as a collection and
then they get distributed out when רבי Rebbi wrote the tractate, when
he sort of edited the תלמוד Talmud or the משניות, Mishnayos, and
the tractates, he took those collections and he like took out the
relevant lines and put them in the relevant places. But here you
actually have the full list. Okay. So that is okay, so we
get that there is a list and we get the individual, why
is the full list presented here as opposed to presented elsewhere? Okay.
Presented elsewhere has the same question. That is true, but there should
be an answer why, what is the choice of the one place
it is presented. Okay. So תנא שבועות שתים שהן ארבע. tana shevuos
shtayim shehein arba. מאי שנא הכא דתני להו לכולהו? mai shna hacha
detani lehu lekulhu? So why here do we have the whole list?
ומאי שנא גבי יציאות שבת ומראות נגעים דלא קתני להו לכולהו? umai
shna gabi yetzios Shabbos umaros Negaim dlo katani lehu lekulhu? Why when
we deal in שבת Shabbos or in the tractate of צרעת tzaraas
of נגעים, Negaim, we do not have the whole list? We only
have the relevant line. אמרי שבועות וידיעות הטומאה דגבי הדדי כתיבן. amri
shevuos viyediios hatumah degabi hadadi kesivan. Ah, because שבועות shevuos and טומאה,
tumah, and this goes back to my point about the analogy being
drawn between oaths and going into the Temple when you are טמא,
tamei, they actually in the תורה Torah appear side-by-side. If you remember
yesterday, I read from the verses where if you make a false
oath, if you make an oath and then you unwittingly are violated
and so on, or if you are טמא tamei and you enter
into the Temple, that you bring this קרבן עולה ויורד korban oleh
veyored of changing value. Okay. So there they appear right next to
each other in the תורה. Torah. So אמרי שבועות וידיעות הטומאה דגבי
הדדי כתיבן, amri shevuos viyediios hatumah degabi hadadi kesivan, they appear right
next to each other in the תורה, Torah, ודמיון הדדי, vudamyan hadadi,
and not only do they happen to appear but they are actually
in the same, they are not just happen to be physically juxtaposed,
they are actually similar, they are in the same פרשה, parsha, they
are dealing with the same issue. What is the same issue? בקרבן
עולה ויורד bekorban oleh veyored with a קרבן korban that is a
value that goes up and down. תני להו גבי הדדי. tani lehu
gabi hadadi. So we have to have those two together. Also for
whatever reason we do not have a tractate that deals with entering
טמא tamei into the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay. So those two
are going to go together. So once those two are going to
go together, ואיידי דתני תרתי תני כולהו, veaydi detani tarti tani kulhu,
since we are going to do two of the list, we might
as well here use the opportunity to do the whole list. Okay.
But again I reiterate my point that the גמרא Gemara is saying
that the emphasis here is that there is some type of analogy
or juxtaposition or similarity between the שבועה shevuah and the טומאה tumah
in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, and that is why not only
is it in the list but we are going to spend two
chapters dealing with it. Alright, and I think we are meant to
sort of see some parallels. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. So תני להו לכולהו. tani lehu lekulhu. So פתח בשבועות
ומפרש
ידיעות הטומאה. pasach beshevuos umefaresh yediios hatumah. Okay fine, we get that.
But why after you, since the theme is oaths, is שבועות, shevuos,
and that is the first line in the משנה, Mishnah, שבועות שתים
שהן ארבע, shevuos shtayim shehein arba, why then do we spend two
chapters dealing with the impurity, right, and with טומאה? tumah? What, we
should jump right into dealing with oaths. So the גמרא Gemara says
איידי דזוטרי מילייהו, aidi de-zutri mileihu, so פסיק שרי להו. pasik sharei
lehu. No, since
since it's short, meaning dealing with the issue of being impure and
going into the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it's now, it's not really
short, it takes two full chapters. It's not like it takes two
משניות, mishnayot, it takes two full chapters. But two full chapters as
opposed to the entire tractate which has how many chapters? It has
seven chapters. Okay, so yes, we'd rather deal with this, it's a
little off topic, it was mentioned second, it was a little digression,
but let's wrap up this little off-topic digression, spend two chapters doing
it, over the next two weeks together or more we'll be spending
doing this. Okay, and then we'll be able to put a full
focus on what the tractate is really about which is שבועה, shavuah,
which is making an oath. Okay, so איידי דזוטרי מילייהו aidi de-zutri
mileihu since its words are relatively shorter, so פסיק שרי להו pasik
sharei lehu you sort of cut it off and you just open
it, you just sort of you get done with it, you untie
it as it were, and then after you're done dealing with it
בתר הכי תני שבועות דנפישי מילייהו batar hachi tani shavuot denafishi mileihu
then we're going to deal with שבועות shavuot which is going to
be which is the focus of our tractate, that there's a lot
to say. Okay, so that's in terms of why our tractate is
structured the way it is. שבועות שתיים שהן ארבע. Shavuot shtayim shehein
arba. Now we're going to get into the actual meat of the
issue. By the way, I should say since we just finished discussing
the whole issue of shaving at the end of מכות, Makkot, that
תוספות Tosfos I for some reason תוספות Tosfos there didn't discuss the
important הלכה halachah issues about it. Maybe it was a different I
think it was a different תוספות Tosfos there, but תוספות Tosfos here
does. And I want to just read you one line if you
take a look in one of the תוספות. Tosfos. If you look
back on דף ב עמוד ב daf bet amud bet in the
תוספות. Tosfos. Yeah yeah, the publisher of the ש"ס Shas had a
couple of different manuscripts in front of him and different schools of
תוספות Tosfos wrote different תוספות Tosfos and there are different authors or
whether the person himself or whether it was authored by his school
and so therefore sometimes they have bigger or lesser treatments of particular
issues. Anyway, here anyway תוספות Tosfos basically if you look at תוספות
Tosfos on דף ב עמוד ב, daf bet amud bet, חייב על
הזקן שתיים. chayav al hazaken shtayim. He says נראה דאף על גב
דעל הזקן אינו חייב אלא בתער, nireh de-af al gav de-al hazaken
eino chayav ela be-ta'ar, even though on the beard you're only חייב
chayav for a תער, ta'ar, razor, remember we just discussed this, כדאמר
בפרק בתרא דמכות, kidamar be-perek batra de-Makkot, which is why we allow
shavers because we say a shaver isn't a razor, דבעינן גילוח שיש
בו השחתה, de-ba'inan giluach she-yesh bo hashchatah, it has to be completely
destroyed, ובהקפת הראש חייב אף במספריים כעין תער, u-ve-hakafat harosh chayav af
be-misparayim ke-ein ta'ar,
by the sideburns you transgress even if you use scissors that are
operating like a razor, which for us we translate into a shaver.
And then he goes on to prove it. רמב"ם Rambam disagrees by
the way. רמב"ם Rambam says that actually you can use מספריים כעין
תער misparayim ke-ein ta'ar for your sideburns. Beard, sideburns or head? No,
הקפת
הראש
hakafat
harosh means your sideburns.
But anyway, but we adopt the position of תוספות Tosfos which is
why you can't use not only a razor, you can't use a
shaver for your sideburns because you can't use even scissors that are
functioning like a razor. Okay, so that's one very important הלכתי halachic
issue about why people like me, right, I shave my beard here
with my shaver in the morning, but I don't shave my sideburns.
Okay, you mean you can't go above the temple.
No, this area here you can now scissors is different. But to
actually use a shaver which gets right against the skin, that you're
not supposed to use in this area.
Show us where the bottom of the.
Yeah, from exactly from here. Now the question is again I don't
want to start an הלכה halachah discussion but as we said, according
to some the whole problem is if you cut off the entire
sideburn and exactly how how do you define it or whatever, but
anyway,
but I wanted you to see that difference. And what about the
little device on the side that you can use that, that's more
like a scissors? Yeah, that's an interesting question. I think it depends
on how close you get it to the skin, because if you
get it right against the skin that might be כעין תער. ke-ein
ta'ar. If you get it like if you hold up the thing
with the scissors and you do like that, then that's okay. So
you have to go at
least to the bottom of the bone, before you use any of
that device. And close to the skin, yeah. Right.
And the next תוספות Tosfos asks the question, if you look at
the next תוספות, Tosfos, ג עמוד א, gimmel amud aleph, ועל הזקן
שתיים מכאן. ve-al hazaken shtayim mikan. נראה דמשחית ונשחת שניהם חייבים, nireh
de-mashchit ve-nishchat sheneihem chayavim, that when it comes similar to the sideburns,
when it comes to the beard, it applies whether to the person
giving the shave and receiving the shave. And then he goes on
to say even if the person giving the shave is not obligated
in מצוות. mitzvot. How would the person giving the shave not be
obligated in מצוות? mitzvot? גוי. goy. A non-Jew. So תוספות Tosfos has
a whole this whole תוספות Tosfos discussed this to discuss the fact
that you're not allowed to go to a non-Jewish barber and get
like a shave with a straight razor. Okay, so you’re going to
expect him to ask us like are you Jewish or not, if
you’re Jewish I can’t give you this to you? You mean it’s
a גוי goy חייב chayav you should say that? No, you receiving
it, it doesn’t matter if it’s not only the one giving the
shave is prohibited, the one receiving the shave is also prohibited. receive
a shave and it doesn't matter from the perspective of the one
receiving the shave whether the one giving it to him is obligated
in מצוות mitzvos or not. So the basic point of this תוספות
Tosafos is don't tell me, hey, I'll just go to a non-Jewish
barber and get him to give me a, you know, a shave
and I'm not doing the hair cutting, he's doing the hair cutting.
So this whole תוספות Tosafos says no, sorry Charlie, it's still a
problem, you know, because, you know, because it's a problem even to
receive the shave, not just to give it. Okay, so I just
wanted to mention that, two important תוספות Tosafos about this whole issue
come up here and not in מכות. Makkot. Let's look now at
the דף daf of the גמרא Gemara at the two dots. Okay.
So a Jewish barber would have like a hard time, meaning like,
you know, some people may just, like, even ask you are you
Jewish, oh, then I can't give, or I can't give you this
haircut. Right, that's a good point too. I hadn't thought about that.
For a Jewish barber that's also true. It doesn't matter who the
one receiving it is. Yeah, I'm pretty sure תוספות Tosafos is explicit
about that as well. I'll have to double-check that, but I'm pretty
sure he's explicit about that as well, that even if that, if
right, that it doesn't matter as long as one of the parties
is obligated, that party transgresses. Okay. יציאות השבת שתים שהן ארבע. Yetzias
ha-Shabbos shtayim she-hen arba. So now we're going to go through the
list before we focus back on, you know, what the פרק perek
focuses on, which is the, which is the going into the בית
המקדש, Beis ha-Mikdash, we're going to focus on the other two that
are fours. Okay, so יציאות השבת שתים שהן ארבע. yetzias ha-Shabbos shtayim
she-hen arba. What is the two which is four ways of carrying
on שבת? Shabbos? שתים, הוצאת העני והוצאת בעל הבית. Shtayim hotza'as he-ani
v'hotza'as ba'al ha-bayis. So the first משנה Mishnah in שבת Shabbos describes
the case, that here I am, I'm in my home, and I've
got a poor person out on the street, in the רשות הרבים,
reshus ha-rabim, in the public domain, that's asking for a loaf of
bread. And it's very nice, if I want to do a מצוה,
mitzvah, I can invite him into my home, have him have a
loaf of bread in my home on שבת. Shabbos. But don't go
ahead and hand a loaf of bread out from your home, your
private domain, out to the עני ani who's standing out in the
street, and that's a form of carrying on שבת. Shabbos. So the
way we sort of imagine, you know, describing the idea of the
transgression of the private domain and the public domain is the issue
of the poor person and the בעל הבית. ba'al ha-bayis. Okay, so
you see I got myself a new marker here. Whatever.
Thank you, got yourself a new eraser.
That's true, very true, good point. There you are in your house,
okay, here's like the window of your house or whatever, anyway, here
you are, right? And here's this poor person in the street. All
right, so, and here's your loaf of bread, okay, whatever.
This is the בעל הבית, ba'al ha-bayis, this is the עני.
ani. So, there are two that are four, the two that are
seen as the primary form of carrying, based on the verse that
משה Moshe said, don't bring any more of your gifts for the
temple, means don't bring from your homes, your private domains to where
we're collecting everything here in the middle of the street, means that
the primary form of carrying in the תורה Torah is going from
the private domain to the public. So the two that the first
two that are seen as the two primary ones in the תורה
Torah is either when the owner stretches out his hand and gives
to the עני, ani, he's going from the private to the public.
Okay, or the other version of that is, the עני ani stretches
his hand in, like Bugs Bunny
or something, exactly.
Well, anyway, he stretches his hand in and picks it up and
then he brings it back out. Okay, so that's the two, two
ways of carrying from private to public
whether you're initiating on the inside or initiating on the outside. And
the way that that's four is just, is just the reverse. The
עני ani brings, puts something, gives something to the owner or the
owner stretches out his hand and takes something from the poor
person. Okay. שתים Shtayim, הוצאת העני והוצאת בעל הבית. hotza'as he-ani v'hotza'as
ba'al ha-bayis. Two, either the poor person is taking the bread out
of the house or the owner's taking the bread out of the
house. שהן ארבע, She-hen arba, which is really is four, there's two
more. הכנסת העני והכנסת בעל הבית. hachnasas ha-ani v'hachnasas ba'al ha-bayis. The
poor person puts the bread into the house or the owner stretches
out his hand and brings the bread into his house. Okay. מראות
נגעים שתים שהן ארבע. Mar'os nega'im shtayim she-hen arba. The spots of
leprosy are two which is
four. שאת ובהרת. Se'eis u-vaheres. The two mentioned in the תורה Torah
is different types of leprosy, one is called שאת se'eis and one
is called בהרת. baheres. You can be very grateful that we are
not learning נגעים Nega'im so we do not have to worry about
what those are and how to describe them. שהן ארבע, She-hen arba,
what are they? שאת ותולדותיה. Se'eis v'toldosah. Oh, because this שאת se'eis
has its subcategories and בהרת ותולדותיה, baheres v'toldosah, this בהרת baheres has
its subcategories. Right, exactly, which is called ספחת, sapachas, which is a
secondary type of a spot, which is just as מטמא metamei you,
but conceptually it's seen as a, as a derivative or subcategory. Okay.
מני מתניתין? Mani masnisin? Five. Now so now we've basically identified the
different parts. Now let's, who is the author of our משנה? Mishnah?
לא רבי ישמעאל ולא רבי עקיבא. Lo Rabbi Yishmael v'lo Rabbi Akiva.
Neither רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael nor רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Why?
אי רבי ישמעאל, Ee Rabbi Yishmael, האומר אינו חייב אלא על העתיד
לבוא. ha-omer eino chayiv ella al ha-asid lavo. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
says you're only transgressed for the future, right? That's sort of like,
what was that movie, Minority Report? We're only going to punish you
for your future sins. No. What he's saying is, sounds like, but
what he's saying is, I appreciate the people who got the reference.
Okay. So anyway, so what he's saying is, is that there's two
types of oaths, right? What is the two which is four by
the oaths? Two things you swear about the past, I didn't do
this, or you know I did this, and two that you're swearing
about the future, I will do this, I won't do this. So
he and then if you transgress, you have to bring a קרבן,
korban, if you did it unwittingly. Okay, so רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael
says you only bring a קרבן korban for the future-oriented because remember
the verse says the person swears
להרע
או להיטיב, le-hara o le-heitiv, right?
And then it says that he brings a קרבן. korban. All of
this is in the context of the קרבן עולה ויורד. korban oleh
ve-yored. So we say, so we say that these are the two,
which is future, you're going to do something in the future, and
then the four that we learn from that plus an extra two
more, which are you're going to, you'll do or you won't do
something in the past. So רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael says, I don't
agree to the two which is four. I say two which is
two. You only bring a קרבן, korban, yeah, if you take a
false oath that's a bad thing about the past and maybe you
get lashes or who knows whatever your punishment is, but it's not
about bringing a קרבן. korban. The bringing a קרבן korban are only
the future. Okay, so our משנה mishna is not רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi
Ishmael. לא רבי ישמעאל ולא רבי עקיבא. lo Rabbi Ishmael ve-lo Rabbi
Akiva. אי רבי ישמעאל האמר, ei Rabbi Ishmael ha-amar, he says later,
אינו חייב אלא על העתיד לבוא. eino chayav ela al ha-atid lavo.
You only bring a קרבן korban for making an oath about the
future.
But you wouldn't get lashes?
Well, I don't know, we'll worry about that in a minute. אי
רבי עקיבא האמר, ei Rabbi Akiva ha-amar, now רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says you do bring a קרבן, korban, you do hold of the
two which is four, you do bring a קרבן korban for violating
an oath future-oriented or past-oriented, but האמר על העלם טומאה הוא חייב
ואינו חייב על העלם מקדש. ha-amar al he'elem tumah hu chayav ve-eino
chayav al he'elem mikdash. But he disagrees with another two which is
four in our משנה, mishna, okay? The two which is four in
our משנה mishna about being טמא tamei and entering into the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, right? So this is what the תורה Torah said
here right by a שבועה. shavuah. It says כי תשבע לבטא בשפתים,
ki tishava levate bisefataim,
okay, whatever לבטא בשפתים, levate bisefataim,
okay, להרע או
להיטיב. le-hara o le-heitiv. So that's the two which is future and
the other thing it says is, what does it say by the
טומאה? tumah? It says
כי תגע בכל דבר
טמא,
ki tiga be-chol davar
tamei, it says
אשר יטמא
בה ונעלם ממנו.
asher yitma bah
vene'elam mimenu. So the simple sense is what's hidden from you is
the טומאה, tumah, העלם טומאה. he'elem tumah. Okay, and that's two because
you can do two things wrong with it. You can eat a
קרבן korban or you can go to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
That's the two. What's the plus two? The plus two is העלם
מקדש. he'elem mikdash. You forgot you were going to the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash and העלם, he'elem, right, קרבן. korban. Okay. So רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Ishmael says I only hold of which העלם קרבן? he'elem korban?
You forgot that you were eating a קרבן. korban.
Oh okay, like העלם קודש he'elem kodesh basically.
Yeah, מקדש וקדשיו. mikdash ve-kodashav. Okay, great.
So רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael says I only hold of these two.
Okay? I don't hold
of the plus two, did I erase the plus
two? Plus two which is past. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says I
only hold of these two. Okay? I don't hold of these when
you forgot the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and
forgot or forgot the קרבן. korban. So neither of them hold of
two which is four for both. Do you get it? רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva holds I hold of this but here only two. רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael says I hold of this but here only two.
So the גמרא Gemara asks a very reasonable question. Nobody holds of
both of the cases of two which is four. All right? So
let's take a look. So the point is that you can you
know according to some people use this part and that part. All
right, let's see. The גמרא Gemara would like one person to actually
be able to hold both positions so the משנה mishna lists all
of them which is somewhat forced. I don't know.
Let's can we not go those
to we have a
whole פרק perek to deal with it.
Okay. So אי רבי עקיבא האמר, ei Rabbi Akiva ha-amar, now רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva holds of the four of the שבועות shavuos but
he only holds of the two of the טומאה tumah cases. So
nobody holds of both cases of two which is four. So the
גמרא Gemara says איבעית אימא רבי ישמעאל איבעית אימא רבי עקיבא. iba'is
eima Rabbi Ishmael iba'is eima Rabbi Akiva. I can tell you it
goes like רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Ishmael, it can it goes like רבי
עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Let's see how it goes like רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi
Ishmael. איבעית אימא רבי ישמעאל. iba'is eima Rabbi Ishmael. Let's say it's
רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Ishmael. So what was the problem with רבי ישמעאל?
Rabbi Ishmael? He doesn't say you bring a קרבן korban for an
oath about the past. Fine. מהם לחיוב ומהם לפטור. mehem le-chiyuv u-mehem
le-pattur. Two which is four doesn't mean you're חייב chayav on all
four. It means I can conceptually describe four types of oaths. There's
two oaths which are in the future and there's two more which
are in the past. You don't get a קרבן korban for all
of them. Okay, but conceptually if we wanted to talk about the
types of Not a terrible read, but the גמרא Gemara says אי
בעית אימא רבי ישמעאל מהם לחיוב ומהם לפטור. ee ba'is eima Rabbi
Yishmael mehem l'chiyuv u'mehem l'p'tur. Say the same for רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi
Yishmael. There are two types of ways of becoming טמא tamei and
violating, which is in the תורה, Torah, that you forgot the טומאה,
tuma, and those you bring a קרבן, korban, which are four. There
are two more types of ways where you forgot that you were
entering into the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, and those you're not חייב
chayav for. So basically what we're doing is we're creating the, we're
listing the possibilities, but we're not necessarily saying that they all have
the same הלכה, halacha, okay? So not a big deal. There are
two which is four, we're not saying they all have the same
הלכה. halacha. So the גמרא Gemara says, לפטור? l'p'tur? What? Some of
them you could say have a different הלכה, halacha, some of them
you're exempt? הדומיא דמראות נגעים קתני, hadumya d'maros negaim katani, it could
have also said דומיא דיציאות השבת. dumya d'yetziyas haShabbos. But the rest
of the משנה Mishnah makes it clear that the two which is
four means it's the same הלכה halacha by all of them. By
the spots of leprosy, the two and the other two, you all
make you are all צרעת. tzara'at. By the שבת, Shabbos, the different
types of carrying is all a violation of שבת. Shabbos. So we're
not just describing the different possibilities. The idea of saying they are
four means the same הלכה halacha applies to all of them, okay?
מה התם כולהו לחיובא, mah hasam kulhu l'chiyuva, the same way there
they're all you're all חייב, chayav, or it all makes you, you
know, makes a person a מצורע, metzora, אף הכא נמי כולהו לחיובא,
af hacha nami kulhu l'chiyuva, here too as well. So don't give
me that that's a cheap answer. I want a better answer. Okay,
fine, let's make it, let's work again. לעולם רבי ישמעאל, L'olam Rabbi
Yishmael, we'll say it's רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. דכי לא מחייב רבי
ישמעאל לשעבר קרבן אבל מלקות חייב מחייב. d'ki lo mechayev Rabbi Yishmael
l'shavar korban aval malkus chayiv mechayev. Who said our משנה Mishnah is
talking about a קרבן? korban? Now the simple sense of course it
is, as that's the comparison of the שבועה shvuah to the to
the טומאה, tuma, is that they're all about the same type of
a קרבן. korban. But what the גמרא Gemara says is no, maybe
when רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says you don't transgress, not you don't,
the two that are in the past you're not חייב, chayav, he
means you don't bring a קרבן. korban. You only bring a קרבן
korban for the future-oriented oaths. But when in the משנה Mishnah it
says two that is four, he means whether it's future or past-oriented,
if you violate it willfully, you'll get lashes. Right, so that's the
way in which you could say they're all in the same category.
They all get lashes. Yes, there's a difference whether you get a
קרבן. korban. Only the two in the תורה Torah explicitly in the
קרבן korban category do you bring a קרבן. korban. You don't bring
a קרבן korban for the past ones, but you do get lashes.
Isn't that a לאו שאין בו מעשה? lav she'ein bo ma'aseh? Which
the גמרא's Gemara going to get to that. Okay, אבל מלקות חייב
מחייב, aval malkus chayiv mechayev, וכדרבא דאמר רבא. u'k'd'Rava d'amar Rava. So
first we have to know how do you know you get lashes
for making a a false oath, okay? Because there's two because when
you make an oath, right as Michael says, there's two ways you
could say you're not doing an act. Okay, well, Michael, you'll have
to figure out we'll have to figure out in your absence which
one you were referring to. But one way of saying an oath
that is not doing an act is that it's just verbal. Does
a verbal act count as an act, right? You only get lashes
for doing an act. How about a verbal act? Okay, that's debated
in a lot of places in the גמרא. Gemara. But the גמרא
Gemara says that by an oath you do, when you make a
false oath, because it says כי לא ינקה ה' את אשר ישא
שמו לשוא. ki lo yenakeh Hashem es asher yisa shemo l'shav. God
will not cleanse the person that takes His name in vain. And
the גמרא Gemara says God won't cleanse you, gets back to the
scene we mentioned earlier, but down here we'll cleanse you. How are
we going to cleanse you? We'll give you lashes, okay? Gets back
to the discussion at the end of מכות Makkos that the punishment
we do down here gets you out of punishment up in heaven,
okay? So from there we learn that for a false oath, we
give you lashes. Now that's a שבועת שוא. shvuas shav. שוא shav
is actually, it's like an oath in vain, okay, which doesn't even
mean it's false. שוא shav is different than שקר. sheker. שקר sheker
is a lie, שוא shav is in vain. So שוא shav would
be you take an oath about something obvious, okay? You know, you
swear that red is red, you know, or you take an oath
on something that is obviously false. You swear that two plus two
is five. All right, that's a שבועת שוא. shvuas shav. שבועת שקר
shvuas sheker is that actually it's not obvious that it's false and
you're deceiving people and it's a lie, okay? So what we have
to do is we have to say the same way we know
you get lashes for שבועת שוא, shvuas shav, because that's our דרשה
drasha that God won't cleanse you but down here we'll beat you
and we'll cleanse you, we'll lash you and we'll cleanse you, you
also get lashes for שבועת שקר, shvuas sheker, for a false oath,
okay? And that's how we're going to get over the first hurdle
to say you do get lashes although it's just a verbal act,
you do get lashes for taking a שבועת שקר. shvuas sheker. Okay,
so let's take a look. דכי לא מחייב רבי ישמעאל לשעבר קרבן
אבל מלקות חייב מחייב. d'ki lo mechayev Rabbi Yishmael l'shavar korban aval
malkus chayiv mechayev. He does give you lashes, וכדרבא דאמר רבא, u'k'd'Rava
d'amar Rava, בפירוש ריבתה תורה שבועת שקר דומיא דשבועת שוא. beferush ribesa
Torah shvuas sheker dumya d'shvuas shav. The תורה Torah explicitly compared a
false oath to a vain oath. מה שוא לשעבר אף שקר נמי
לשעבר. mah shav l'shavar af sheker nami l'shavar. The same way a
vain one is past-oriented, a false one is also past-oriented. Now what
does it mean past-oriented? Meaning number one is the comparison is to
tell you that you get lashes. The same way But here's what
it's saying though. Only there, remember, there's two which is four, right?
So there's four ways I can take a false oath. What are
the four ways I can take a false oath? I can swear
I did something in the past that I didn't do, or swear
that I didn't do something that I did do. Okay? Those two
are past oriented. Those two are like a שבועת שוא, shvuat shav,
are like an oath in vain. Why? 'Cause as soon as I
utter it, I have done the violation. Right, when I take an
oath that 2 2 is 4, or 2 2 is 5, which
is a שבועת שוא, shvuat shav, either way, it's obviously true or
obviously false, I am taking an oath in vain that is a
violation the moment I utter it. If I take an oath about
something I've done in the past, okay, if and I'm lying, it's
also a violation the moment I've uttered it. So that type of
past oriented שבועת שקר shvuat sheker is like a שבועת שוא shvuat
shav and it's obvious that you would get lashes. Okay, but now,
a future oriented שבועה, shvua, I take an oath that I will
do something and I don't do it, or that I won't do
it and I do it, that's not, that's of a different category
and that's not, that we cannot learn out explicitly from this comparison
that you are going to get lashes. Okay? So let's take a
look. What we have is the following, okay? Okay, there you are.
There's the timeline. What should be your past and what should be
your future? Okay, this is yesterday. This is tomorrow. Look at my
spelling. Alright, okay, so here, if you say right something, if you
say this is a שבועת שוא. shvuat shav. 2 2 4, or
2 2 5, okay? That's a שבועת שוא, shvuat shav, okay? And
there you get lashes. Okay, now similarly if you say something about
the past, right? I had eggs for breakfast, okay, or whatever. Okay,
you had something you did or something you didn't do. Or that
would be I didn't have eggs for breakfast, okay, whatever. Okay, that
is a case of שקר, sheker, right, לשעבר. l'she'avar. Okay, and that's
similar 'cause as soon as you utter it, right, you are doing
the wrong thing. Okay, so if here you get lashes and we
learn that out from לא ינקה השם, lo yenakeh Hashem, then here
you get lashes. Okay, so even though all you did was something
verbal, you get lashes. Now contrast you to the following cases. I
will have eggs for breakfast tomorrow. I'll say I will eat eggs
for breakfast tomorrow, for breakfast tomorrow. Or I won't, okay? That's the
two, by the way. I will or I won't, you know, you've
done the you will you won't you. Now this is what the
תורה Torah is talking about. Right? This is להבא. l'haba. And this
is the case in the תורה Torah which is להרע או להיטיב,
l'harah o l'heitiv, to do something, okay? That's the case in the
תורה. Torah. That case we know you get a קרבן. korban. Now
what we're going to have to figure out is do you get
lashes for that? Alright, is that clear? So the problem of the
two which is four is that these two future oriented you get
קרבן. korban. We're trying to say that the משנה Mishna is not
talking about קרבן, korban, the משנה Mishna is talking about about lashes.
So lashes we know, here's that big divider, right? Lashes we know
is about the past. That's as soon as you utter it, it's
false. קרבן korban we know is about the future. So if the
משנה Mishna isn't talking about קרבן korban and the משנה Mishna is
talking about lashes, we want to see that you get lashes now
in the case of the future. Alright? That pretty clear? Yes? Alright,
so let's see so now let's see what we say. So it
says like this. So let's read that again. So בשלמא bishlama אכלתי
ולא אכלתי achalti v'lo achalti כרבא. k'Rava. So good. So if it's
in the past, I ate eggs for breakfast, I didn't eat eggs
for breakfast, that's like רבא, Rava, you get lashes because of the
connection to a שבועת שוא, shvuat shav, to an oath in vain.
שלא אוכל ואכל. shelo ochel v'achal. Now what about future oriented? I
won't eat eggs and you eat eggs. נמי לאו שיש בו מעשה
הוא. nami lav sheyesh bo ma'aseh hu. That's also you get lashes,
you violated and you actually did an act, not just a verbal
act. You ate the eggs. Right? So if you say I will
eat eggs, so now there is going to be two cases. I
will eat eggs and is I won't eat. So here you say
you will eat and then comes tomorrow and here you are sitting
down at your table—I have to draw someone sitting—and here you are
you're eating your eggs. Okay. Okay, you're eating your eggs. I don't
know why that's eggs. Okay. So when you do this act, that's
when you did—that's your act, that's your violation—this is when you transgress,
okay? So here you've transgressed and you've done an act, you're eating
the eggs. So no problem. I get that you get lashes here.
Here it's only verbal. But we're learning out from a oath in
vain you get lashes because of the moment it came out of
your lips it was false. Here it came out of your lips
and you didn't do anything wrong. When you eat them, you're actively
transgressing, you get lashes. That I get. So this case I get
why you get lashes. But "I won't eat," I'm sorry, I did
it wrong. This case, you get lashes. You say you won't eat
and you eat. Okay. But when you say you will eat, you
transgress just by doing nothing, by sitting around and not doing anything,
right? So where are your lashes? Your lashes aren't for the moment
of utterance because it wasn't false at that time and you can't
get lashes for not eating, for not fulfilling it because you're being
totally passive. So where are your lashes in that case? All right.
So let's take a look. Are you getting this? Yeah, Dave? All
right, fine. All right, it says 3:14. But isn't he violating? I
mean, you're violating, but passively. In the passive sense? Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Nobody's questioning that you transgressed, okay? But you transgressed, it really should
not be just transgress. Since you're transgressing through an act, you get
lashes. Okay, here you transgress, you act—let me write it this way:
You actively transgress and therefore you get lashes. Here it's only passive.
So where are the lashes? Okay. So we've explained three of the
four cases. Exactly. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, הא אוכל ולא
אכל, ha ochel velo achal, if you say you'll eat eggs tomorrow
and then you don't, אמאי, amai, why would you get lashes? לאו
שאין בו מעשה הוא, lav she'ein bo ma'aseh hu, it's a negative
transgression without an act. Because the גמרא Gemara says, קסבר רבי ישמעאל
לאו שאין בו מעשה לוקין עליו, kasavar Rabbi Yishmael lav she'ein bo
ma'aseh lokin alav, maybe he holds that you get lashes even for
a passive transgression. אי הכי קשיא רבי יוחנן אדריבי יוחנן, I haki
kashya Rabbi Yochanan ad Rabbi Yochanan, if that's true, we have a
problem that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is not consistent. Why? דאמר רבי
יוחנן הלכה כסתם משנה, de'amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha ke'stam mishnah, רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan says we normally go by our סתם משנה. stam mishnah.
And our סתם משנה, stam mishnah, right, that says two which is
four, now we're saying that our סתם משנה stam mishnah is referring
to lashes. So the conclusion would be that our משנה mishnah is
saying that if you passively transgress, right, you get lashes. Right? Because
we're saying our משנה mishnah is talking about lashes. So if that's
true, our משנה mishnah would say now, okay, קשיא רבי יוחנן אדריבי
יוחנן. kashya Rabbi Yochanan ad Rabbi Yochanan. דאמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כסתם
משנה, de'amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha ke'stam mishnah, which would mean that for
לאו שאין בו מעשה lav she'ein bo ma'aseh you would get lashes.
ואיתמר, ve'itmar, but we have another teaching. שבועה שאוכל ככר זו היום
ועבר היום ולא אכל, shavuah she'ochal kikar zo hayom ve'avar hayom velo
achal, sounds exactly like we were talking about. Exactly the same case.
Somebody takes a שבועה shavuah that I'll eat this loaf of bread
today and they sat around and didn't eat it. רבי יוחנן וריש
לקיש, Rabbi Yochanan ve'Reish Lakish, it's a debate of רבי יוחנן וריש
לקיש. Rabbi Yochanan ve'Reish Lakish. דאמרי תרוייהו, damrei tarvaihu, or not a
debate, they both agree on the הלכה, halacha, they debate the reason.
דאמרי תרוייהו, damrei tarvaihu, they both say אין לוקה, ein lokeh, you
don't get lashes for passively not doing your שבועה. shavuah. רבי יוחנן
אמר אין לוקה משום דהוי לאו שאין בו מעשה Rabbi Yochanan omar
ein lokeh mishum de'havei lav she'ein bo ma'aseh because you're being passive,
וכל לאו שאין בו מעשה אין לוקין עליו, ve'chol lav she'ein bo
ma'aseh ein lokin alav, anything you're passive you don't get lashes for.
וריש לקיש אמר אין לוקה התראת ספק היא, ve'Reish Lakish omar ein
lokeh hasrat safek hi, because the warning is doubtful. If you tell
me at 6:00 AM, Dov, we're warning you, you better eat eggs
today, if you don't eat eggs, you're going to get lashes. And
I say, I don't know and I don't care, okay, but at
that moment you don't know that I'm going to transgress or not.
I might not transgress because I'm not going to transgress until the
end of the day. Okay, so it's considered ספק safek because if
you assume—you could actually say is the problem is not just ספק,
safek, the problem is that the warning did not immediately precede the
act. But if you flip it the other way, if the warning
has to precede the act, then the choice I make immediately after
the warning to not eat the eggs right now, it's doubtful whether
that's going to lead to transgression. It'll only be determined, right, by
the end of the day whether my not eating eggs now led
to transgression. So that's called התראת ספק. hasrat safek. So therefore they
both agree that you don't get lashes, whatever the reason. So now
we've got a problem. We said the point of our משנה mishnah
was that you get lashes on all these cases. And רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan is supposed to go like a סתם משנה. stam mishnah.
But רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says you don't get lashes when you
passively did not fulfill your שבועה. shavuah. So that's—so we've got a
problem here. So the גמרא Gemara says, here's the גמרא's Gemara answer:
רבי יוחנן סתם אחריני אשכח. Rabbi Yochanan stam achrini ashkhach. רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan found another סתם משנה stam mishnah that led him to
say you do get lashes even if it is a passive act.
What's his סתם—I'm stam sorry, if it is... No, the other way.
That even though our סתם משנה stam Mishnah says you get lashes
for a passive act, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was able to conclude
you don't get lashes for a passive act and he was able
to go against our סתם משנה. stam Mishnah. Why? Isn't רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan supposed to go like a סתם משנה? stam Mishnah? Because
he found another סתם משנה stam Mishnah that says you don't get
lashes. דתנן, detnan, סתמא אחריני אשכח. stama achrini ash-kach. האי סתמא. hai
stama. Which other סתם משנה stam Mishnah did he find that allowed
him to say you don't get lashes? אילימא האי סתמא, i-leima hai
stama, the following one, דתנן, detnan, אבל המותיר בטהור, aval hamotir b'tahor,
somebody that leaves over meat of a קרבן korban even if it's
a טהור tahor קרבן korban that your meat you're allowed to eat
and you transgress by leaving it over and not eating it by
the morning, והשובר בטמא, vehashover bitamei, or if you break a bone
of a קרבן פסח korban Pesach that became טמא, tamei, אינו לוקה
את הארבעים, eino lokei et ha'arba'im, you don't get lashes. So why
not? We had this in מכות. Makkot. בשלמא שובר בטמא, bishlama shover
bitamei, I get why you don't get lashes for breaking a bone
of a פסח Pesach that is טמא, tamei, דכתיב ועצם לא תשברו
בו, dichsiv v'etzem lo tishberu bo, don't break a bone in it
in the קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, בכשר ולא בפסול. bekasher velo b'pasul.
So בו bo means the one you're allowed to eat you're not
allowed to break a bone. If it was a invalidated קרבן פסח,
korban Pesach, you are not you don't transgress. That's the prohibition of
breaking a bone. It doesn't imply when the קרבן פסח korban Pesach
is טמא. tamei. But why don't you get lashes by leaving over
the meat of a קרבן? korban? That is a clear negative prohibition.
Okay, אבל המותיר בטהור, aval hamotir b'tahor, leaving over the meat of
a כשר kosher קרבן, korban, מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, why don't you
get lashes? לאו משום, lav mishum, isn't it because דהוי לאו שאין
בו מעשה, d'havi lav she'ein bo ma'aseh, it's a passive act? וכל
לאו שאין בו מעשה, v'chol lav she'ein bo ma'aseh, any transgression that
is a passive transgression, אין לוקין עליו, ein lokin alav, you don't
get lashes. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says we got a problem.
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan holds you don't get lashes for a passive
transgression. If our משנה Mishnah is talking about lashes, then one of
the cases you do get lashes for a passive transgression. That does
not fit with רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan position. So the answer is
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan has another משנה Mishnah that backs him up.
There's another סתם משנה stam Mishnah that says you don't get lashes
for a passive transgression and that's the משנה Mishnah about not getting
lashes for leaving over the meat of a קרבן. korban. Okay. So
you got so that allows this משנה Mishnah we're saying is saying
you get lashes for passive transgression, but רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan doesn't
have to go by it. He's got this other משנה. Mishnah. So
the גמרא Gemara says וממאי, u'mimai, since when is that משנה Mishnah
over there, why is that necessarily support this idea of not getting
lashes for passive transgression? וממאי דרבי יעקב היא דאמר לאו שאין בו
מעשה אין לוקין עליו, u'mimai d'Rabbi Yaakov hi d'amar lav she'ein bo
ma'aseh ein lokin alav, how do you know the משנה Mishnah about
leaving over the meat of a קרבן korban follows רבי יעקב? Rabbi
Yaakov? רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov is the one who's of the position
you don't get lashes for a passive transgression. ואימה דרבי יהודה היא,
v'eima d'Rabbi Yehuda hi, maybe that thing that you don't get lashes
is based on a different reason why you don't get lashes for
leaving over the meat of a קרבן, korban, not because it's passive.
There's a רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda reason. What's the רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda reason? ומשום דבא כתוב ליתן עשה אחר לא תעשה, u'mishum d'ba
kasuv litein asei achar lo ta'aseh, because there's a positive מצוה mitzvah
that's coming to fix it. Just a little review of מסכת מכות,
masechet Makkot, right? You don't get lashes for passive, you don't get
lashes for something called a לאו הניתק לעשה, lav hanitak l'aseh, it's
a negative prohibition but to be fixed somehow with a positive עשה,
asei, and maybe that's why you're not getting lashes by the meat
of a קרבן. korban. הלאו הכי לוקי halav hachi loki what, not
for that you would get lashes? דתניא, detanya, we learn in a
ברייתא, braisa, לא תותירו ממנו עד בוקר, lo sasiru mimenu ad boker,
do not leave over any meat till the next morning, והנותר ממנו
עד בוקר באש תשרופו, vehanotar mimenu ad boker ba'esh tisrofu, and leave
over any meat it'll be burned by fire. בא כתוב ליתן עשה
אחר לא תעשה, ba kasuv litein asei achar lo ta'aseh, the תורה
Torah is coming to give you a positive עשה asei that follows
the negative one, the prohibition, לומר שאין לוקין עליו דברי רבי יהודה,
lomar she'ein lokin alav divrei Rabbi Yehuda, to tell you she'ein lokin
alav, you won't get lashes because you can fix it by doing
the positive עשה. asei. רבי יעקב אומר לא מן השם זה, Rabbi
Yaakov omer lo min hasheim zeh, רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov says nah
you don't even need that reason, okay? אלא משום דהוי לאו שאין
בו מעשה, ela mishum d'hava lav she'ein bo ma'aseh, it's because you're
passive, ולאו שאין בו מעשה אין לוקין עליו, v'lav she'ein bo ma'aseh
ein lokin alav, and it's also only because you're passive that's why
you don't get lashes. Okay, so here what we have, we have
our סתם משנה stam Mishnah here, okay? Okay, this is our סתם
משנה, stam Mishnah, and the case for I will eat extra breakfast
tomorrow and then you don't eat and you're going to get lashes
seems to tell us that you get lashes for, you know, even
passive transgression, even passive transgression. Okay, that's what our משנה Mishnah is
telling us. Now that could be fine except that רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says you go by a סתם משנה, stam Mishnah, so we
would have to go by this הלכה. halacha. But רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan himself says you don't get lashes for a passive transgression. So
how you work it out? We've got this other משנה Mishnah about
נותר. notar. נותר notar no lashes. So that other משנה Mishnah tells
us the opposite הלכה, halacha, no lashes for passive, and that's why.
How do you know that's the reason?
Maybe the reason is because there's a connected to an עשה. asei.
So we don't have a clear משנה Mishna that tells us that
you don't get lashes for something passive. And the way we're reading
it this משנה Mishna is telling us you do get lashes. So
how does רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan reject this משנה? Mishna? And you
can't say he rejects this principle of lashes by embracing this משנה,
Mishna, because this משנה Mishna might not be about the fact that
it's passive. So we don't have רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan having another
משנה Mishna that allows him to say that you don't get lashes
for a passive transgression. So let's see what the גמרא'ס Gemara's answer
is. אלא האי סתמא. Ela hai stama. Here's the סתם משנה stam
Mishna that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan has. אלא האי סתמא אשכחה, Ela
hai stama aschkcha, which is exactly about our case, exactly about passively
violating an oath. שבועה שלא אוכל כיכר זו, Shvua shelo ochal kikar
zu, an oath that I won't eat this loaf of bread. שבועה
שלא אוכלנה, Shvua shelo ochlena, and then he take another oath which
is the repeat of the first one. ואכלה, Ve'achala, and you ate
it. אינו חייב אלא אחת, Eino chayav ela achat, you only get
one set of lashes. Why do you get one set of lashes?
Because the second שבועה shvua is you're already obligated, מושבע ועומד, mushba
ve'omed, you can't take a שבועה shvua to obligate you to do
something you're already obligated to do. So the second שבועה shvua didn't
take effect. Okay you got it? So you took an oath not
to eat and then another one not to eat, the second one
didn't take effect, the first one did, and when you violate it
you get one set of lashes. Okay but that is when you
violated it actively. You said you won't eat the loaf of bread
and you ate it. Okay. זו היא שבועה, Zo hi shvua, and
then the משנה Mishna says זו היא שבועת ביטוי שחייבין על זדונה
מלקות ועל שגגתה קרבן עולה ויורד. Zo hi shvuat bituy shechayavin al
zidona malkot ve'al shigagata korban oleh veyored. This is the שבועה shvua
of that we transgress when you do it willfully you get lashes
and when you do it unintentionally when you violate it you bring
a קרבן. korban. So now the גמרא Gemara says what does it
mean this is the one that we're talking about? So the גמרא'ס
Gemara's interpretation is זו היא דחייבין על זדונה מלקות, zo hi dechayavin
al zidona malkot, this one you get lashes because you violated it
actively. אבל אוכל ולא אכל, Aval ochal velo achal, if you said
you would eat and you don't eat, לא לקי, lo laki, you
don't get lashes. Okay so basically this משנה Mishna the way we're
reading it, our opening משנה, Mishna, two which is four, says you
get lashes for passive transgression of a שבועה, shvua, but there's another
משנה Mishna that doesn't exactly say the opposite but we're going to
read it to say the opposite. You have another משנה Mishna that
says you get lashes when you actively violate and we're going to
read it to say you don't get lashes when you only passively
violate. Alright, so you got it? There's one סתם משנה stam Mishna
here that seems to say if the way we're reading it that
you get lashes for even passively violating a שבועה shvua and another
סתם משנה stam Mishna that by implication says you don't get lashes
for passively violating. So now the גמרא Gemara just has one question
left. Which is what made רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan favor one משנה
Mishna over the other? He had his pick of which משנה Mishna
to go by. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says מכדי. michdi. Let's
take a look. האי סתמא והאי סתמא. Hai stama vehai stama. You
have two סתם stam mishnas. מאי חזי דעבד כהאי סתמא לעבד כהאי
סתמא. Mai chazei de'avid kehai stama le'avid kehai stama. Why does רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan follow the סתם משנה stam Mishna that implies you
did not get lashes for passive violation of a שבועה? shvua? Why
not follow our משנה Mishna that says that you do get lashes
for passive violation? So the גמרא Gemara says ולטעמיך. ule'taimach. רבי, Rabbi,
according to you, רבי גופיה היכי סתם הכא הכי והכא הכי? Rabbi
gufei heichi stam hacha hachi vehacha hachi? How did רבי Rabbi himself
put two contradictory סתם משנה'ס? stam mishnas? The משנה Mishna that opens
our tractate says you do get lashes for passive transgression and a
משנה Mishna coming up not too much later says you don't get
lashes for passive transgression. So what is רבי Rabbi doing contradicting himself?
אלא מעיקרא סבר לאו שאין בו מעשה לוקין עליו Ela me'ikara savar
lav she'en bo ma'aseh lokin alav וסתמה. ve-stama. That this was a
history that this was in transition. Initially, the initial ruling was that
for a passive transgression you get מלקות, malkut, and that was our
first משנה, Mishna, the סתמא, stama, and he taught it as a
סתם משנה, stam Mishna, our first משנה Mishna is you get lashes
even for passive violation of a שבועה. shvua. והדר סבר, Vehadar savar,
and then he thought better of it and he thought אין לוקין
עליו, ein lokin alav, you know what? You don't get lashes for
passive. The only one you get lashes for is when you actively
violate. This סתמא stama that he taught as a סתם משנה stam
Mishna later in the tractate. ומשנה לא זזה ממקומה. Umishna lo zaza
mimmekoma. And he wasn't able to uproot the original משנה Mishna from
its place. Like we said once the original משנה Mishna had been
taught over many years and adopted by the students and everybody knew
it you can't tell people stop learning this first משנה Mishna it's
not correct you know so you have to you know so it's
sort of like you know what is this like you know by
אחשורוש Ahasuerus or whatever? Yeah you're about to say the same thing.
You know we can't we can't revoke the earlier decree. So nobody
is going to stop learning this first משנה, Mishnah, but I'm going
to teach you a new משנה Mishnah that's going to make it
clear that you only get lashes for an active violation. Okay? So
now the way we are reading is how does our משנה Mishnah
mean two that is four since nobody holds two that is four
by קרבנות Korbanot by all the cases, neither רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael
nor רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? So the answer is, we're talking about
lashes, two in the past are clear that you get lashes, two
in the future, which is when you get a קרבן, Korban, it's
not as clear you get lashes and the חידוש Chiddush is you
do get lashes even for a passive non-performance. Okay, but a later
משנה Mishnah teaches against
that
and the
later משנה Mishnah is the one that we rule by that by
a passive violation you actually do not get lashes. Okay, we will
end for today.